[Music]
all right hello and welcome this is
active lab live stream number 40.0 it's
march 10th 2022.
welcome to the active lab we're a
participatory online lab that is
communicating learning and practicing
applied active inference you can find us
at the links here on the slide
this is recorded in an archived live
stream so please provide us with
feedback so that we can improve our work
all backgrounds and perspectives are
welcome and we'll be following video
etiquette for live streams
check out
activeinference.org to learn more about
the lab
all right
in today's number 40.0 the goal is to
learn and discuss
this very cool paper that was published
on archive on december 30th
2021 a free energy principle for generic
quantum systems by chris fields carl
fristen james f glazebrook and michael
levin
and
just like every video
it's going to be just a conversation
going over some parts of the paper it's
not a review or a final word
and if anything it's um a cry for help
or at least a cry for participation
because there's so many areas where
somebody with different experience or
more knowledge about any of these
domains could connect some dots or
give some useful comments or critiques
so
especially with this video
though blue and i had help from our
colleague jason larkin with many of the
details there's just so much to unpack
so
we'll try to make this a
useful dot zero
and then we're really looking forward to
the dot one and
dot two and so on when we'll be able to
really go into some of these directions
so
i hope if you're watching live or
between now and the dot one
check out the paper and listen to this
discussion that we'll have now and ask
some questions because this is just
the beginning of a few new threads
probably more than the answering of
questions especially to any desired
level of like completeness or
applicability so it's just the beginning
that's what the dot zero is about it's a
new decade 40.0 so
um
we'll just uh introduce yourself and
then go through a bunch of the paper
and yeah thanks again to jason for a lot
of help in blue
for awesome work on the slides too okay
so
um
i'm daniel i'm a researcher in
california and i'll pass to blue as
facilitator
blue knight i'm a researcher in new
mexico and i have to shout out to daniel
too because you're always saying thank
you to me but you know we all have to
say thank you to you for providing the
affordances to be here and you know
discuss these awesome questions um big
paper i am uh excited to delve into this
i think it will you know start a lot of
new trails so i think um
and also to bring back mike levin and to
bring back chris fields um and to bring
back carl firsten back to the active lab
to discuss the dot one with us hopefully
um okay so is there anything particular
that you are excited about daniel or do
you want to just power through it let's
get let's jump in
all right
so this paper really was trying to unite
um
the quantum principles and the free
energy principles so quantum mechanics
and kind of delving into that and we
will see some threads carry over from
the last time that we had chris fields
on here maybe the last time we had mike
levin on here also um so how is the free
energy principle related to quantum
mechanics what does the fvp gain from
quantum what does quantum gain from the
fep
are we using the fep now to model
quantum systems and why are we pursuing
this intersection so this was kind of
like
the big questions kind of maybe we can
start to answer with this paper
um so
we are here
daniel what's this map about
um
it's a question we're gonna probably ask
ourselves multiple times so we can
insert it like a little emoji
but we can think of
among the axes of variation or
variability that we're going to explore
or where we're going to tune our regime
of attention or what perspectives we're
going to take it's going to be like
along two axes
ranging from on the right side fep
active like
to the left side which is like pre or
non
active slash fep
it's the x axis and the y axis
is the continuum between
quantum which we'll probably nuance and
hear many perspectives of what isn't
isn't quantum but just to summarize it
by saying quantum and not quantum like
pre or non-quantum approaches and so
quantum fep
is in the upper right corner
and we can think of it as being like
connected in different ways
to quantum non-fep in the top left the
blue and then fep but from a non-quantum
perspective like
all pre now
fap active in green
and then what are all the other
connections
and so who's right who's wrong who's
useful
where's their pragmatic value where is
their epistemic value what are we really
talking about do we agree on the
phenomena
where where is their agreement or
disagreement
where are we in this complex landscape
so i think in mechanics we refer to it
as classical mechanics and quantum
mechanics so now we will be this is like
the dividing point maybe between
classical fep and quantum fdp perhaps
let's see where it goes
so the aims and claims of the paper
there are pretty much three and we'll
revisit these at the summary because
we're going to just give you
a broad overview of the summary of
results right now
given the standard free choice
assumption the intuitive ideas of an
agent or information gathering and using
system igus
can be fully formulated within
background independent scale-free
quantum information theory
the second claim is that fep can be a
quantum theoretic formulation that
renders it applicable to generic quantum
systems and do you want to read the last
one daniel uh three when formulated as a
generic principle of quantum information
theory the fpp is asymptotically
equivalent to the principle of unitarity
cool do you want to read the first
section of the abstract
all right
the free energy principle or fpp
states that under suitable conditions of
weak coupling random dynamical systems
with sufficient degrees of freedom will
behave so as to minimize an upper bound
formalized as a variational free energy
on surprisable also known as
self-information
this upper bound can be read as a
bayesian prediction error
equivalently its negative is a lower
bound on bayesian model evidence also
known as marginal likelihood in short
certain random dynamical systems events
a certain kind of self-evidencing
so here we reformulate the fep in the
formal setting of space-time
background-free scale-free quantum
information theory we show how generic
quantum systems can be regarded as
observers
which with the standard freedom of
choice assumption become agents capable
of assigning semantics to observational
outcomes
we show how such agents minimize
bayesian prediction error in
environments characterized by
uncertainty insufficient learning and
quantum contextuality
we show that in its quantum theoretic
formulation the fep is asymptotically
equivalent to the principle of unitarity
based on these results we suggest that
biological systems employ quantum
coherence as a computational resource
and implicitly as a communication
resource
we summarize a number of problems for
future research particularly involving
the resources required for classical
communication and for detecting and
responding to quantum context switches
it's like okay cool what does it mean
how will it be useful
yeah um so we're gonna unpack a lot of
this and hopefully give everyone a good
framework with which to kind of go
forward into the dot one and dot two
maybe a little bit of background
understanding um the paper is very beefy
so we'll do our best to kind of
lay the framework down
they give us a good road map so there's
five sections the introduction
physical interaction as information
exchange and several subsections within
that repeated measurements and system
identification and subsections the fep
for generic quantum systems and the
discussion
and i think that they actually outline
what's in each section so we'll give you
that outline overview as we go through
the paper as well
so just we're going to use we're going
to actually reuse some slides from actin
stream number 17
that was when we had chris fields
presenting information flow in context
dependent hierarchical bayesian
inference
i think contextuality is like an
underlying thread that's pretty
important here today so chris kind of
lays that out in the um in that paper
and so if you want to get into
that and dive deeper into two spaces and
channel theory which we'll talk about a
little bit but um
yeah that's there so use that for a
resource
just
one foreshadowing here
the two pieces that they claimed in this
paper as their goals was to
connect contextuality to category theory
and shoe spaces
and then connect that yellow formulation
to hierarchical bayesian inference
more looking like the statistical models
and so this paper is kind of building a
category theory bridge with bayesian
graphs and statistics and category
theory and then that's probably going to
hinge over to a few other areas
cool so we can jump right into the
introduction
um
here and we're just going to highlight
some keywords as we go through the
authors didn't really give keywords for
the paper um which i'm kind of grateful
for because there's so much so many
other things to unpack here so they um
highlight some things about the fep in
the words of the authors
since its introduction is a theory of
brain function the variational free
energy principle has been extended into
an explanatory framework for systems at
all scales the fep is the statement that
any measurable bounded and
macroscopically
system will behave to satisfy these
requirements requirements
what else daniel
it was just cool how they brought in the
fep
as being the overarching level as
describing how these particles
do
two things which is possess internal
dynamics that are conditionally
independent
from the environment
and performing this self-evidencing
feature
by returning to some non-equilibrium
steady state and so just which parts of
the fep they entered in at or emphasized
which we can assume are
setting the stage up in their mind best
for the interfacing or the on-ramping
into quantum
where somebody interested in like a
system or integration other than quantum
might take a different approach
cool i think that they borrow also from
our particular physics and we're going
to talk about particles and they talk
more about particles in the discussion
and maybe we can have a deeper
conversation about those in the dot one
and dot two but they say the markov
boundary of any particle
um that's an open exchange with external
states via its markov boundary
underwrites conditional independence
between its internal states and the
external states of its environment by
localizing and thereby restricting
information exchange
so the markov boundary separates
internal and external states by
mediating their exchange we've seen that
before
cool so what is active inference daniel
can you break it down for us two cents
overview
that blanket that blue just described
with the insulation
incoming statistical dependencies can be
interpreted as perception
and outgoing statistical dependencies
can be interpreted as control
and depending on the situation and
what's zero and what's not zero that can
have a lot of dynamics that are similar
to some other
classic settings in decision making
gambling
experimentation
quantum
measurement
in this paper
very cool
uh so what is quantum theory
um
this is cool just some pictures and it's
connected in
to many many different uh fields so
there's a cool kind of concept map of
where quantum theory intersects
um but you know the quantum theory here
is the idea that that
all physical systems can including the
environment can be considered observers
that act on their surroundings to
prepare them for subsequent observations
that's
become common in quantum theory
replacing the wave function collapse
postulate of traditional quantum
mechanics with interaction induced
decoherence which is like the
dissipation of quantum coherence this is
like the thing that generates classical
information
and they say indeed while quantum theory
was originally developed and it's still
widely regarded as the theory
specifically applicable at the atomic
scale and below
since the work of wheeler feynman and
douche dutch douche
it has over the past few decades been
reformulated as a scale-free information
theory and is increased increasingly
viewed
as a theory of the process of
observation itself
so um yeah i think like when we think
about quantum we think about the
observer at least i do like i think
about the observer phenomenon just the
act of observing a system changes the
system
so that's kind of a fundamental thing
that comes to my mind what comes to your
mind daniel when you think about quantum
theory
uh
if reading that leaves me uncertain
whether we're talking about like organic
chemistry and the pi orbitals and
covalent bonding and emission and all of
those things that particles do
which is what it sounds like they're
talking about in this orange part
a theory specifically applicable to the
atomic scale and below
and then this blue part makes it sound
like they're opening it up into a much
larger space so i think we'll probably
learn a lot about that what does quantum
mean here are we talking about electrons
and protons
or is this something that is like
bayesian inference in that it's scale
free or scale a priori or scale friendly
or something like that
nice scale independence
so we're gonna jump right in so section
two they talk a lot about physical
interaction as information exchange and
that's something i wonder also like is
you know we have the classical mechanics
and do the laws of quantum always apply
or at some scale are they you know not
applicable or can we
extend them into some like theory of
everything like are we getting there
maybe
but here in this section they say that
they use the category theoretic
formalism of channel theory
to formalize the operational semantics
of natural languages so they develop a
generic formal representation of quantum
reference frames and show how the
non-commutativity of quantum reference
frames induces quantum contextuality and
i had fun really digging into this
at a level that i felt comfortable
explaining it
so i'm excited to see if i if i
fungal it or how it goes let's see
okay
what is quantum
wow
when physical interaction is used
information exchange why is it quantum
becomes obvious the fundamental quantum
quantum of information is one bit one
unit of entropy
that one system exchanges for another so
one bit one quantum of information is
the answer to one yes or no
question
that is quantum
do you want to add anything here daniel
this is the block text is from
the paper
and just one
piece that will be interesting to
explore is just how does time and
temperature
come together
like
i had just heard or thought more about
the space required for storage and
not really seen it as much connected to
the speed of obtaining
that yes or no answer
at different temperatures
and what that might mean for
biological or for digital systems
but i'm sure that's a very
um
[Music]
foregone conclusion maybe working with a
quantum device but
new to me and jason was like oh yeah of
course that's the case
and they they talk a lot so
foreshadowing they're gonna um you know
really present this within like a
facetime independent context which is
kind of cool and then like link it back
to time which that kind of gets
a little interesting
all right
so
moving on
uh hilbert spaces
um
so
daniel do you want to say a bunch about
this or what do you want to say about
this and then i'm going to highlight
some stuff
i'll just read what they
um wrote
oh here's the the red part is was our
comments on what they wrote people can
pause it to read what they wrote the
hilbert spaces contain all states
described as a vector
and this is one way that qubits are
constructed
by relating two levels of a system like
electrons in a ground or excited
superposition
and then the collapse
into one or those other
bands
and so that's more of like a
uncertainty to discrete transition
but then in the limit of high
temperature there's a lot of blur
or experimental factors that can be
modeled as blur
that results in a smoother distribution
of outcomes
and
[Music]
here this hilbert space
is describing how the experiment is set
up and the information that's being
modeled
at a given time
so the state of
that this space consists of the options
for
is like the just the experiments space
including
the total target system and the observer
maybe
so i like this quote at the end that as
fuchs put it
infinite dimensional hilbert spaces are
from an information perspective merely a
useful artifice
permitting computation with differential
equations and they they contain all this
possible states in an experiment as
vectors so
um
there's more to read about that um
and also the mathematical notation if
you're curious
about cats and bras and some of these
brackets that we had to to dig through
to
find solid ground
yeah okay so the principle of unitarity
is the principle that observable
information like energy is neither
created nor destroyed by physical
processes
and i thought that this was interesting
so time reversal symmetry
is essential for the conservation of
information
so a system is time reversal symmetric
if its equations of motion allow perfect
prediction
of the starting point based on knowing
the state of the system at any given
time
so like if you know time whatever x time
steps you can still
say something about the starting system
because you can run it forward and
backward in time i mean there were some
cool things like about if you pulled up
a mirror that's that's like enables the
time reversal so some things go forward
but like the spin of an electron is spun
backwards in time right so it's like
those kinds of things um
like our some things are parallel and
some things are opposite in time
reversal symmetry but um anyway i
thought that was interesting and
fundamental so kind of the principle of
an eternity and also because we're going
to talk about time
in a cool way i think
um okay
so
yeah
unitary do you want to say about unitary
daniel i said a little bit so let me
pick out some things here that you want
to talk about
okay
this was all with just jason
helping us and again it's like an
opportunity for anyone who's familiar
with these
to uh formalisms to help us a little bit
more through but just to pick up on one
point just
as blue mentioned like we're doing
experiments where it doesn't matter what
time we started at
in a sense like it may matter in the
sense that the different times lead to
different results but
a statistical framework for observation
that can
cut through some of the parts of the
experimental context
that are not relevant
to compare different events that happen
a different time
in a unified statistical framework
and so that was what led to this
principle of unitarity that the total
probability distribution is preserved
with like a mass of one
so that there can be information
evolution but it's happening in a
certain space
where there's a certain invariance that
allows useful computation to happen
cool
oh yeah conservation of probability so
that's something that maybe came up um
like the probability that a particle is
somewhere like it's somewhere there's a
hundred percent probability that the
particle is somewhere so it didn't
disappear so that was another kind of
interesting point we were talking um
before this
i mean that's kind of what how you get
the conservation of observable
information as well
um
okay
separability and holographic
encoding
okay this one
just to
uh briefly look at a previous slide i
think this was from 32
we were looking at sparsely coupled
systems
from a matrix perspective and so the
dense coupling of like subunits one
through six with each other was mainly
like within the click of the red or the
blue but then there's these off
diagonals that reflect the sparse
coupling of denser clicks
and so
in section 2.3 of this paper
they're
also talking about
coupling
patterns in systems
specifically ones that have a
separability
so like one of those blocks could be the
experimental system the quantum computer
and the other one of the blocks could be
the experimenter and then there could be
sparse connectivity reflecting the
experimental apparatus
but that was being approached from a
quantum holographic angle
also setting up for a markov blanket
take
cool so one sentence on this
page that i think is important is
underlined here the entanglement entropy
is a mutual information measure that
detects quantum correlation or coherence
between a and b
um and so
that defines separability and if either
a system is separable or it's entangled
so separable states are also called
decoherent and entangled states are also
called coherent so just just point out
as we go forward and kind of dive a
little bit deeper into the math it it's
kind of like if it was parametric
classical statistics we would say
uncorrelated or correlated if it was
information theory we'd say no
information or yes it gives information
bayesian graph yes it has causal
influence or no it doesn't and then this
is the quantum take yes it's entangled
or no it's not entangled
also don't forget conditional dependence
or conditional independence so where
where is it conditionally dependent um
and we know that like the markov blanket
can help to define conditional
dependence um when we've looked at
active inference in the past
yeah
um okay cool so
where do you want to talk about the
hamiltonian
or not at all what do you want to say
not at all okay
so there's one cool thing that i want to
point out here
um you know we talked about like which
interactions strong interaction
different time frames and how these are
going to vary as we go forward um but
but here i really just wanted to point
out that that this h of a b is like the
hamiltonian so we're talking about
matrices separability interacting
matrices conditional dependence just on
the last slide um and so the
interaction between the hamiltonian of
the matrix can be decomposed
into this h a b where this is like the
interaction between a and b
so ajb can be looked at as we go forward
as the energetic interaction between
matrix a and matrix b state a state b
position a position b or um they give it
to us in a very generic form so i didn't
really know how to apply that going
forward but maybe if the authors were
listening they'll come in and rescue us
um that's the only thing i really wanted
to point out from from that side
and then this is kind of cool so
this this equation six which we just
looked at um which is the energetic
interaction between a and b
um this is physical interaction which i
guess is
that could be physical interaction
between a and b that also be energy
right matter equals nc squared
physical interaction equals
thermodynamics times yes or no questions
so it's cool the authors say this
formulation emphasizes what quantum
theory is about the process of obtaining
information obtaining information from b
requires in particular that a acts on b
by asking questions as wheeler puts it
no question no answer all inference in
this framework is active inference
equation 6 does not allow
passive perception to be a physical
process
super interesting agreed from a lot of
angles
it almost takes it
to a level we haven't seen
from just saying well perceptual
inference even the generative type so
not just the signal processing but even
a predictive processing
generative
framework for perception that doesn't
take action into account is incomplete
hence the motivation for active
inference and this is
somehow escalating that
into
saying that all inference in this
framework is active inference and i
wonder if that's because like a frame is
always needed some kind of generative
model is always needed
as a recognition model dual for any
observation so if you're in the business
of making observations you're in the
business of generative model
modification
one way or another
or you're not the kind of thing that
does either of those but they might come
into play
in the minimal active entity or the
thing that can be modeled as a minimal
active entity
and so
there's a lot of interesting areas and i
think it's also quite interesting with
the natural language equation
so how should we read that dot
thermodynamics
what
yes no questions and then
times or what does it mean
yeah there's the category theory like
that that dot operator i forgot how to
read it
so hopefully um it'll be rescued
um but yeah i i read it at times because
you know i'm old school
so
going back to that same equivalent
i thought that this was important it
involves no assumptions about space-time
objects or motions it is strictly
topological
given separability it identifies a
boundary fancy b
between a and b
at which
the energy interaction physical
interaction between a and b is defined
so i guess that would be like a space
well i guess it's not space it's not
space it's not time it's a physical it's
an energy interaction hiv
um anyway yeah
and this is the markov blanket fancy b
holography connection which is that all
the information that is making the
sparse connectivity of a and b
we're talking about systems that have
like this screen slash blanket slash
experimental apparatus
fancy b
and the properties of it for a system
that might be making
classical like measurements
or maybe it's making quantum
measurements so
implicitly the prior work
had been thinking about what was on the
other side of that
experimental apparatus
from a classical or from a non-quantum
perspective we'll see
and this is taking it more into asking
what kind of mathematics would be needed
to look at it if it were a quantum
system that were being investigated
cool
and i think that takes us into
figure one
so here daniel was foreshadowing doing a
great job of the holographic screen
so this is a holographic screen fancy b
separating systems a and b with an
interaction
h a b
given by equation six and so
this
says that this this screen can be
realized
by an ancillary array of non-interacting
qubits that are alternately prepared by
a and then measured by b
uh qubits are depicted as the spheres
here
um and there's no requirement that a and
b share preparation and measure
measurement bases
so these are uh quantum reading
or quantum reference springs so this is
like they share the ability to prepare
or measure that would be like quantum
reference frame and we're going to get
into the quantum reference frames just
here in a couple slides um i think with
a pretty good example
cool
anything to add or do you want to like
unpack it with the next couple slides
um just thinking about this as like a
quantum holograph is sort of
the generalization maybe
of thinking about this in the classical
information what if this were
the chat between blue and i so we could
have different perspectives different
reference frames different semantics
but if we're not in the same chat room
then we're not in the same chat room
that's like the holographic screen or
the observable that's getting passed
between these two systems a and b
and they don't have to be two people it
could be like a person and some other
system on the other side of the
holograph slash information channel
and the whole question
is
what kind of math describes that
classical information channel case
and how is that similar or different or
compatible or whatever
with thinking about it not as a
information bit from a standard
probability distribution but like a
quantum information bit with a complex
statistical distribution
nice
um
so they describe the holographic screen
actually um
as they say the holographic screen fancy
v
has an obvious interpretation in the
language of the free energy principle
and active inference it implements the
markov blanket that separates
from b so we've seen the markov blanket
before and you know mentioned it here
but but i think that they are going to
you know implement this holographic
screen as this markov blanket um yeah
perfect cool
oh and then the quantum reference frame
fun
so uh
here they say we show in particular that
the fvp emerges naturally in any setting
in which an agent or particle deploys
quantum reference frames namely physical
systems that give observational outcomes
and operational semantics to identify
and characterize the states of other
systems in this environment
and and so this was kind of a cool um
figure that i that i pulled down
so it's like a man
on the train
to the man the train is moving and to
the person on the train the man is
moving right and so it depends on your
perspective
and this is this is
kind of what a quantum reference frame
is getting at here so um this says
quantum features such as quantum
superposition are only defined relative
to an observer when we look at the train
from the point of view of an observer
standing on the platform the train looks
in a quantum superposition of different
positions however an observer sitting on
the train sees the observer on the
platform and the ball in a quantum
superposition so it's a cool
illustration of just kind of how things
look differently depending where you're
standing
okay this is awesome i like how you
brought in the art and the images are a
little subtly different but then in a
way that really makes one think
and the classical case would be what if
both of them were moving or still
and then they only got to get a
frame update once every two seconds or
once every five seconds so then there'd
be like still an uncertainty
distribution but it'd be a classical
parametric statistics or information
theory uncertainty about location
and that's going to be the big question
how is that
variance estimation that we've already
been exploring
and that type of inference related to
quantum information where there's
something a little bit
bigger and more complex or different
than just simply low sampling rate
leading to positional uncertainty of a
massive train that's not subject to
so-called quantum effects
cool
um
did you want to what so this is kind of
cool do you want to unpack this slide
here daniel
i'm just looking forward to what the
free choice assumption means
in
setting but
we just highlighted what is this all
going to say about free choice this
specific slide but also the broader
discussion
so i i agree too i think the free choice
aspect is cool um here the authors say
provided a and b are separable assuming
that there are no super determinist a
priori correlations
um
z a and z b what is the z i'm not sure
what the z is
oh
choices of z
so the z is the choice the choice of a
and the choice of b are uncorrelated
this is the free choice assumption free
choice is often claimed to be essential
to science as a practice
if it characterizes any bounded system
consistency with quantum theory and
special relative relativity together
requires that it must characterize all
systems so free choice of a basis
introduces quantum noise that is
indistinguishable observationally from
classical noise and and noise is going
to become important here um as we move
toward the end of the a and z
so
yeah
anyway that's cool
okay
[Music]
nice
so here they talk about um the z-axis in
figure one i should have pasted figure
one in here
um they say that the z axis is a
reference frame free choice of the axis
generalizes the free choice of the
reference frame encoding each qubit on
the
holographic screen fancy beat right
so um yeah
and the part in red looking forward to
unpacking
a qrf cannot therefore be fully
specified by any finite bit string it is
non-fungible in the terminology of
citation 40.
it's the quantum active
nft crossover
that we all needed
we have it but we need to explore it and
find out what it means
super cool um
and they say that they consider a and b
to be isolated during the time interval
between
preparation and measurement steps um and
i think that we'll get into that
um
in a little bit more like preparation
and measurements as we talk about time
and memory and coding
um
yeah and that's what this um
nine formalism is roughly describing
something like that
there's yes
yeah
what is happening with it
so it says the idea of a computation um
is this so you have uh bits
that have one time step going to bits at
another time step and then you have the
um markov blanket in one time step going
to another markup blanket at t plus one
and then this is it za is that free
choice that's in there
oh
no it's if so i'm not sure what that one
is but
yeah we can we can unpack that more i uh
i will unpack some of the later math but
um
this i think it's just important to
establish the quantum reference frame
anyway yeah that's good cool okay
um
next where are we
ah here we go see i'm gonna start to
unpack some math now when i when i start
to roll out the variables here we go
okay
so
we will be interested in what follows in
quantum systems considered to be
observers that deploy one or more
distinct quantum reference frames to
measure particular subsets of the bits
encoded on their boundaries slash markup
blankets um and yes these will d
effectively decompose the holographic
green fancy b into disjoint sectors that
we will label e for the observed
environment f for the unobserved
environment and y for the memory sector
prospectively
so um yeah we're gonna we're gonna break
that out
um
i think
yeah attention also so they really talk
about the sectors
as a sense right like so i have like my
vision sector my hearing sector my taste
sector right and so like i'm making
observations of my environment with all
these like my temperature sensing sector
so there's all of these different ways
um you know to observe the environment
with different sectors
so yeah cool it's kind of like saying
you win some you lose some
you don't play
every game
it's kind of like whatever space we're
talking about here which happens to be
this boundary that has all these
interesting properties
there's some that are being observed
some that are being unobserved and a
special sector that gives continuity of
information in some way through time
yeah
um so this is cool here free choice of a
decomposition of a holographic screen
fancy b
interceptors with different quantum
reference frame induced semantics is
indicative of agency
so i like that and i'm curious to um
unpack that maybe a little bit more
something for to ask the authors about
in the dot one
yeah or also all non-trivial agents are
cognitive systems that engage in active
inference
what
is non-trivial
who
like how do we escape or how do we
escape this infinite
multi-perspective
multi-scenario universe or do we just
have a way of working with that
i do think that they get into
non-trivial here in a little while um
but yeah they say a non-trivial agent is
a system with internal dynamics that
breaks the swap symmetry of its boundary
markov blanket holographic screen
however they're going to start to use
these things interchangeably so i'm just
going to keep saying holographic screen
fancy b
um but but i guess if your internal
dynamics don't break the swap symmetry
or
right like if your internal dynamics are
it are
um trivial or like not relevant
um or if you don't if they don't have an
effect on the boundary maybe that's that
becomes trivial
yeah wondering if that's the mirror
versus adaptive active inference
boundary that we've discussed or what
what this maps to
where does this kick in or not so we'll
explore it though
it totally seems like it's definitely
the mirror versus active inference
that's how i interpreted it as i was
reading it so
it sounds like that to me oh
and okay now we're gonna head into some
17 related
information because they're going to
turn this discussion from qrfs
as reference frames
to channel theory
which is going to enable this context
switching discussion that's important
later so this is brought up
in number 17
and 17.1 is where we had chris fields
and
uh great discussion there so continue
blue
cool
um yeah so
channel theory of quantum reference
frames
so i think we've said channel theory is
an application of category theory
to two spaces and i'm not gonna read the
paper here but i'm going to go back to
some of the slides that we used from 17
because i think that we kind of
unraveled it there in a way that was
maybe digestible more so than reading
you know equations off of a paper
um so this is the true space
daniel what's a two space so k is a set
a are objects x are attributes
a two space
fancy a
over the set k
is the relationship
between the objects a
and their attributes x
i thought of it just like a computer
function
like in python or any language that's
just taking in three kinds of data
the set the objects and the attributes
so
describing
a large variety of things
but it's just kind of integrating those
three types of data
in a principled way
and
enabling transformations between
different representations that might
look very different or allow for
different implementations but also
commonly use
like all of this information or even
just a subset of the information because
that just throws out information which
you can always do
i really like the python example so like
if k is the python dictionary a are the
keys and x are the values like you can
describe the relationship between the
keys and the values
with a chew space like that is that what
the shoe space does so like you could
say you know your keys are apple orange
banana and your values are red orange
yellow and so then the two spaces
how you describe that relationship color
something like that
cool okay
so going into channel theory and how two
spaces um
work how channel theory works so it says
in channel theory two transforms become
isomorphisms
which are natural maps between
classifiers
so classifiers link tokens to types that
encompass them like for a stoplight a
set of tokens would be red
green and yellow so that is the set of
tokens
i think this just builds one level on
what you described which is instead of
just the data structure
of just saying this is what the function
is requesting or this is why it's being
stored in memory this is like saying
we're going to interpret some of these
edges and relationships as classifier
mappings or infomorphisms like
information sharing or statistical
dependencies or some other type of
informational edge
but on that
space that we've been discussing
yes so so they take it to um a
diagrammatic level where at the center
it's almost looks like a pyramid so
there's a c
um and this this core c is the
information channel this is the
infomorphism that allows semantic
information and this i thought it was
very cool that it's very different from
shannon information it's not just bits
it's like the meaning behind the bits um
like you can say you know you can see
the word um
bank and are they talking about a
riverbank um the bank that holds your
money or like a bank shot in pool like
there's some underlying
i i would dare to say context
that is important for not just the
letters b a and k in that order so it's
not just the tokens in the particular
order but it's like the semantic context
that allows transmission between
classifiers so i look at this like a
shared memory so like if we look at the
classifier a1 here which would be
stoplight the tokens are red green and
yellow
classifier a2 would be motorist actions
the tokens would be stop go forward or i
say proceed slowly but it's really get
out of the intersection right like
that's what yellow means um and then
there's other classifier types could be
like pedestrian actions child's game
actions like when you're playing red
like green light do you run do you stop
like freeze um
so or do you walk right so there's all
these different um
classifiers that can then map via a core
information channel c
shared memory semantic information
between those
classifiers
cool okay
so
going on they build
from this pyramid they invert the
pyramid um to form this cone cocoon
diagram
so
they say
that
a commuting finite cone
diagram is made of a cone which is the
upright pyramid and a cocoon which is
the inverted pyramid on a finite set of
classifiers
um it
illustrates commutativity so
specifically these operators
g12
g23 like you can go all the way out to
the set like there's a commutativity or
like a um
superimposability commutativity between
with a shared infomorphism if that makes
sense it also captures this more subtle
duality between
processes um it enables object files
tokens and histories to be viewed not as
tokens but as types that organize
um respectively trajectory components
features and feature-based singular
categories and and make them mutually
consistent collections so like where you
have all of those um
classifiers they are they're
consistent across the board
so you can use them to map and unmap
right
if i can just give a take on this
so g12 is saying that there's a
relationship between
a1 and a2 it could be like appending by
one row or maybe changing one little bit
through time or having some ability to
translate like a state machine or
something like that
let's just
say that there's some relationship and
then there's also these f functions that
allow the a's to be part of a shared
context like the pedestrian scene that
makes sense
and then
that is shaped like a cone
that is kind of like sense making
that semantics is making sense and then
this cocon or the diamond shape
is where there's c and d who are both
like cognitive
sense making frames
and then now they're having a shared
holograph
a or shared access
and then it's that
is a different object with a different
geometry
yeah that would be like i'm looking at
the same set of classifiers that you're
looking at and we both see we both know
what they mean we both know that red
means stop and
um greedy means go
semantically exactly
right right or red could mean apple
depending on depending on where you're
going with that right so it could be it
could be an inside joke
yeah
um okay cool so there's the cone cocoon
hopefully that was um unpacked with some
level of uh
intelligibility
so
now we can move into figure two
where they attach this cone cone diagram
to measurement operators
any set of measurement operators
that
are
used to measure
the um states on the
boundary that defines
the relationship between a and b this
hiv between system a and system b
[Music]
were the scientists we cared about r
context c we're system a we're making
measurements from our perspective of a
screen
and we're setting the context of
interpreting those observations in this
situation
totally um i could definitely be
standing on the other side of that
holographic screen making my
measurements from d from the inverted
from the upside down pyramid but they
would be left and right pointing
measuring onto the same screen if i was
system b and you were system a in that
kind of context
cool
anything else to add
no
awesome
okay um so this is just some more i
think this slide talking about the cone
cone
diagram
but but something that's
to point out that there's the dual
construction that is when it commutes i
think i did say that already so when the
infomorphisms on the same classifiers
where all the arrows are reversed when
it's reversible then that's a commuting
cone cone diagram
so non-community is the opposite of that
right so we're going to talk about
non-commutativity as we go forward
and here what's one thing that i think
is happening hopefully is like we have
been discussing this in the context of
two different observers having the same
semantics from the same screen c and d
and then they say if c equals d or c
prime equals d prime
then
you can sort of draw another
consistent world and this is sort of
like a recognition semantics
and then the outcome is like an
operational or generative semantics in a
different way because it's like
generating the observations or something
like that but there's going to be like a
duel between the diamond and the
hourglass
nice
cool
okay
um all right here we go
more of this um
commutativity so so here they talk about
commutativity as bayesian coherence now
we talked a little bit about quantum
coherence earlier but there's this
they're bringing this notion of bayesian
coherence up so viewing commutativity
and bayesian
coherence as fundamental to the
definition of measurement like if i
measure the
length of the salamander and daniel
measures the length of the cylinder
salamander there there we could get the
same answer or not um so
and hence also to the definition of
preparation or action on the environment
so this suggests this born rule
which is that's what you blew up daniel
don't know what it is let's learn about
it
yeah
okay yeah that was that one's um right
let's learn that let's let's let the
authors unpack that one for us
yeah oh yeah that's the rule
so here blow it up again for me oh i'll
blow it up actually myself
so
yeah too far
so they say the probability of obtaining
x
to state x is the sum of
observations over states is that
observations in the states i should have
defined these then the probability of
obtaining
a measurement is it a measurement as an
observational outcome
uh in the description for coherently
assigning amplitudes to components
okay so anyway we can let the authors
unpack that one for us i can't do it
all right repeated measurements and
system identification so this is section
three moving on
we develop in section 3 a generic formal
description of how one quantum system
identifies another quantum system as a
persistent entity a thing so here
they're going to talk about thingness
and measures records and compares its
states by deploying
deploying specific sequences of quantum
reference frames and so like how do i
know that daniel is a different thing
than me right
um yeah that's cool sometimes i think
we're the same thing because we're doing
the same thing at the same time
is there a thing
is there a group thing
that's a group thing
our consensus
we're having a thing at my house
that's it
all right
um so they break this section so these
sections get really awesome so memory
time and course grading
the idea that a system must possess a
quasi-non-equilibrium steady state
solution to its density dynamics and
hence be restricted to trajectories in
its classical configuration space that
do not diverge exponentially over time
in order to be observable as a thing
immediately raises the issues of time as
the measurable duration and of memory as
persistent over measurable time
and so that they show in this figure
that the agent a
can only detect changes in
the nest density and employ them as
bases for inference if actions
and actions if a can write time ordered
records
to subsequently read from the memory
sector y so here the memory sector is y
um the environment is e
and this g i j
here i think it's better done in the
next one oh yeah perfect we have the
next screen right here yep um so eij is
this um a time clock a time step
from one memory that's the dynamics of
internal time internal clock that's what
it is of
the agent
um
we talked already about the different
parts of the screen and how some are
being observed some are unobserved and
then there's the memory sector and here
like the um unobserved environment
is the
biggest set i think it's like
mostly at least in this image
and so one question is just what does
this represent in terms of our computers
or our sensory apparatus
and how is it related to some of the
work that they like cited and some
related
work
about attention and bayesian graphs
this is a cool representation also like
notice that your observations are
different and not overlapping with from
your memory
like if your old memory the new
information isn't coming in
if you're not paying attention to
anything it can't have an effect like
that type of thing
right and so this is an illustration of
quantum reference frames required to
write a readable memory of an observed
environmental state
e
so e and y read the state from e and
write it to y respectively
and the clock is a time quantum
reference frame that defines the time
coordinate a so
at the time step you read the
environment and then you write it to
memory
y
cool
little perception action loop with
memory
yeah
okay four yep in a loop sorry cool
awesome
the figure four
um
it's a memory read write cycle
defining
one tick from i to j of the environment
so
here it's like you
read from the environment
measure or read measure and then write
prepare so like you prepare for the next
time
step
all quantum reference frames and the
comparison functions are implemented by
the quantum dynamics ta which is the big
block arrow
so if this were like an eeg headset that
was measuring at 100 hertz 100 times per
second that would be like 100 classical
information reads per second and then
you could do signal processing
i think this is kind of like
the time step is the sampling frequency
of the experimental apparatus that's
defined by this partitioning
of the blanket fancy b
holograph and then sub sectors
with these different interpretations of
being like observed unobserved or memory
components
and and the authors say here they say
formally we think of this pa
as the weighted sum of all possible
paths
from the boundary boundaries
from the boundary the fancy b at one
state to the boundary the fancy b at the
next state so that is the internal
dynamics are how the holographic screen
is shifted from
t to t plus one
and also this is where there's the cone
so the the b are like those that line of
a's that are all lined up and then now
it's bottlenecking this is the hourglass
and then going back out
yes
should superimpose those
um figures for next time yep
um yeah all right then memory time and
course grading
so the internal dynamics that operate on
those states to maintain a
non-equilibrium steady state density
are spatially localized inside of the
boundary
and the boundary represents a hilbert
space where we talked earlier um and
it's not a physical space-time
decomposition
so the boundary b is all those little
spheres still
what is memory
we'll discuss it
yeah and importantly they say figure
four illustrates an important
distinguishing distinction between
classical and quantum representations of
dynamics
um classical physics assumes a space
time in betting
and the
quantum does not
interesting
yeah i'm curious about the self
evidencing that they mention here also
i'll have to ask them about that
okay
okay cool
learning and generative models i'll let
you take this one away
um
this kind of
took us almost briefly out of the
quantum but just
to give an example of a simpler thing
that this is like an elaboration or a
generalization of a bayesian approach
like calm and filtering
which is just taking it's like a
dragging an estimate through time as new
information comes in
and so that's what's happening in a
sense here with formalism 27 there's a
prior and a posterior
and that's moving forward so it's kind
of like using this dragging
filter
through time
if that were classical information and
then there's something different
happening with quantum
and that's that that piece that we're
gonna keep on returning to but this is
like a bayesian
analog
and now the math is
being
used to describe these quantum systems
yes okay moving on section 3.3
identifying and measuring systems
embedded in e
so we've so far considered only
observers a that measure the states of
their observed environments e without
decomposing
e into systems that have their own
specific states
and the question of how an observer
distinguishes a system from the
environment
in which s is embedded
is central to classical cybernetics so i
think that that's um important like
are the other agents do they matter are
they just part of the environment like
there's always that
um question of of you know is is it its
own thing that other person over there
or it's just my perception of my
environment
and the second part there is like it's
um that sort of entity niche
differentiation or delineation and then
under the rubric of object persistence
the conceptuality of thickness
to cognitive and developmental
psychology so that's like children with
peek-a-boo and so it's like what
connects the child playing peek-a-boo
to the cybernetic entity differentiating
causes
and how does quantum
with its observer
based relationality
connect those areas
so here they use a special
delineation for an environment that
indicates the remainder of e when other
systems in the environment are removed
and the question of how an observer
distinguishes an external system from
its surrounding environment prior to and
as a precondition for measuring some
state of interest
is um not something that people
traditionally address because it is
thermodynamically and computationally
difficult demanding
special requirements on the observers
cool
all right
so figure 5 shows us the system i think
it just shows us like
pretty much where we are systems s
you know here you have a and b
identifying
requires identifying some proper
component r that maintains a constant
state or a density of time average
samples as the pointer state
of
pi right so
you need a pointer to point to the
system
um
or density of time average samples of
interest varies oh so like as this goes
to attention right so what is your
what are you pointing to
oh another way i was kind of seeing this
one was um this the
it's like a clock hand so this could be
like a time scenario or it could be
quantum with like the spin or with the
angle in a complex field or something
like that but you can decompose the
total system s
into the time invariant part which is
like your python data structure and
that's like saying here's the the
structure of the variables
and then just like the variables
themselves that are time variant which
is like the clock hands so they'll be
like the body of the clock that's time
invariant
and then there's the parts that are time
varying
i don't know how that
r and p
and s partitioning connects back but
that's what this kind of looks like
yeah
i'm also kind of unsure about
the pointer states and but i think it's
the interest varies right so um
yeah
which i think i think that points to
attention like as your interest as your
point of focus shifts like what are you
pointing to because like as you look
here
in one direction there's a set of
variables that are there in that
direction like this wall that corner
this refrigerator or whatever and then
as you shift here your
interest or attention is shifting to a
new set of variables but you still know
that that other set of variables is
there that goes to the object permanence
that we were just talking about before
so like i know that refrigerator was in
my first point of view but it's not in
my second point of view but i know that
it's still there um that that to me kind
of is how how i think about this the
pointer
uh it'll be for the authors to maybe
unpack this one a little bit more for us
um
oh okay we did talk about the markov
colonel versus the marco blanket daniel
you you so eloquently explain it to me
just one possibility is the blanket is
the set of states that insulate the
internal and the external making them
conditionally independent and then the
markov kernel could be like that applied
through time
and it's kind of like a arima model you
could have like a temporal depth of an
auto regression and then the temporal
depth of the markov kernel through time
would be like what time steps
are able to
carry forward
but let's discuss that with people who
know better
yes
cool okay good um
all right so non-commutativity
uh context switching
so we talked about
non-commutativity we talked about what
commutativity means and so
non-commutativity would be
the opposite of that um
so here they say as emphasized by bohr
100 years ago a finite quantum of action
partitions the set of all possible
quantum measurement operators into a set
of complementary non-commuting pairs the
most well-known being position and
momentum so if you're trying to measure
the position of a particle you can't
simultaneously measure the momentum of
the particle at the same time so that's
non-commutativity
yes and so
why does context switching matter
they say an observable
an observer a capable of switching
between non-commuting quantum reference
frames must to maintain an operable
memory implement a clock that is
invariant under basis rotations
on
the energy between a and b or the
physical interaction between a and b if
measurements made at clock ticks i and j
do not commute however the corresponding
clock operations will not commute
um so
non-commutativity forces ta which is
time or the time
step that it takes to record a memory to
be unidirectional and hence memory
records to be encoded irreversibly with
an accompanying expenditure
so the internal clock thus defines ta as
entropic time i thought that was super
interesting so it's not like actual time
but it's like time that you paid entropy
for like time that entropy was expended
for
i'm on the clock
time requiring work right or
something to that end
all right
uh
cool so context switching between
non-commuting quantum reference frames
like position and momentum
while holding the other
quantum reference frame constant so
that's the one that's constant is here
the one that's ref
in this figure 34 or equation what is
this thing it's a diagram that's what it
is so in this diagram number 34
um these different pointer sectors u and
v
could be like the different um
non-computing
and then you have overlapping but
mutually communicating operators
in a canonical canonical context switch
so
that's like someone could be standing
not at the
train platform or on the train and be
observing both of those people
i suppose
different frame a bigger a bigger
context they each have their own local
coherence but it's interoperable so it's
part of a bigger umbrella which is like
the big c at the top
cool
okay okay
good
so
that's diagram 34. if it fails to
commute
then the observables are
non-co-deployable
so that's like position and momentum
those are
non-co-deployable
observables so non-commutativity in the
in diagram 34
has been specified in terms of
non-existence of a consistently
definable joint probability distribution
of conditionals
so that's like the conditional
independence right
this non-co-deployable
co-deployability of observables amounts
to the occurrence of intrinsic quantum
contextuality in relationship to that
diagram so this goes really back it
speaks a lot to
what um chris talked to us about when we
did number 17.
so let's get notes on this stuff
yeah for sure
um
so they say in 4.2 below that context
switching
increases variational free energy by
generating prediction errors um and like
if you're in one context and you have a
prediction
and then you move to another context
with the same prediction your outcome's
going to be
different so it increases very
variational free energy
which makes minimizing very variational
free energy and complying with the fvp
more difficult so like going from my
same generative model from one context
to another context to another context
makes it hard
but can lead to radically better
generative models so you're always
updating your gen your model becomes
more generalizable generalizable under
different contexts
so yes quant context switching poses a
fundamental challenge to any classical
formulation of the fep and a fundamental
explanation i've not heard that before
for quantum formulation
um
i wonder if this provides like some
evidence for us having a shared reality
and i i've um brought that up a couple
different times too
here
cool it's the fact thing or expression
which is to be explained or explicated
nice okay now let's get to the paper
what do you think blue
we're finally here um
we made it this is the best part
uh yeah the fvp for generic quantum
systems so all that background was to
lead you here to the um to this place
where we are now so how the fep emerges
in this setting um and we're gonna look
at its asymptotic behavior um
considering how it addresses the
fundamental
problem that's posed by quantum context
switches
all right
we're getting there
you want to take this one
we're going to go into more detail so
that we can
get a lot more in to this dot zero but
we've seen the variational free energy
in the context of perceptual inference
where there's a surprisal and a
divergence term that gets bounded so
this is kind of like the snapshot
question given the incoming sensory
observations
how should i update my generative model
it's learning it's like a perceptual
common filter
yes
it doesn't have action involved
nice
um they have this formulation of
prediction error
and they this is actually from um
section 3.2 it's a representation of the
prediction error of
system a or agent a
so this e-r-e-k
so k we'll just let's go through these
black ones first so k is the internal
time clock so agent a's internal time
clock ta it counts it it ticks it up
so fancy b is the holographic screen
pb is the dynamics of the interaction
partner b
and then this m sub e with respect to k
is the observable behavior of the
holographic screen fancy b
localized to the sector e up to time t a
equals k so like up to up leading up
into this point um so is the observed
environment just to connect it to the
previous formalism e is the observed
environment that is it so here this m a
e this is the agent a's generative model
of the action of the undo un known
dynamics pb
with respect to time i think oh yeah
on the markup or the markup boundary
holographic screen fancy b in sector e
the environment that we looked at
which is kind of like saying you only
need to have a generative model on where
you're expecting to find observations
if you're going to measure just the
thermometer you make a generative model
with just a thermometer and that's how
you get the cone cocon diamond
hourglass
that isn't like with extraneous or
redundant or incompatible elements
so here this um equation prediction
error it's like er sub
parenthesis k
um this is the
agent's agent a's total reducible
uncertainty about agent or system b
at time t a equals k
so so this is like
the uncertainty about another system
within the environment that's why the
system separation that we saw in figure
5 was important so if we're going to
define us
we're going to look at how other systems
interact on the holographic screen and
then we're going to think about what can
we predict what that system is doing or
not like the environment's not doing
anything because it's just sitting there
it's the environment but
that's at any given time step snapshot
um so it is therefore an upper bound on
the surprise um reprisal analogy to f of
pi that we just looked at earlier that
daniel mentioned the upper bound on
surprise
cool okay here we go getting into how
the quantum does the fvp
all right
so
a generic quantum system a
will act so as to minimize er sub x for
each deployable quantum reference frame
x so
a system a has different deployable
quantum reference frames that's
analogous to a sense i have hearing
vision taste smell temperature sensing
etc many different deployable quantum
reference frames and
i will minimize
my total reducible uncertainty
at each time step for each quantum
reference frame
yes
still there
cool
okay
so a trivial agent can be viewed as
executing a trivial quantum reference
frame
as only exercising choice of basis for
writing to and reading from
the holographic screen fancy b as a
whole and so satisfies the fep trivially
okay
let's have a let's have a round table on
what that means
we should do it
yeah
four point two
that's it or forty point one we'll be
there's equation forty nice
there it is
all right
so
the authors say uncertainty and
prediction error and hence variational
free energy is generated in the current
formalism
by system a's in principle ignorance of
both the state of b and the dynamics p
of b of its interaction partner b
as the bits a reads from
the boundary fancy b
are written by
p b this is like the the agent or system
b is writing
to the boundary
so a's ability to predict the future
states of its observable sectors and
hence to minimize that er sub x for each
quantum reference frame x
through equation 40 which we just looked
at and we're going to look at it again
depends on its ability to predict the
behavior
of pb locally on each observable sector
so i have to
be able to predict how daniel's going to
smell how he's going to look so so my
ability if i'm looking at my other
agents in the environment
over each what temperature he's going to
be is he going to have cold hands or
cold feet or something like that
but my ability to minimize my
variational free energy over another
system in the environment
depends on my ability to predict their
behavior writing to the environment
on all of those quantum reference
sectors
good enough good enough
okay
an animal for example must employ its
available senses hence its observable
sectors to predict the nutritional value
of food
okay
here we go
so
this is where i got it gets a little
fuzzy for me
so
uh i was good up until this point
um they say the weak interaction limit
that allows separability between a and b
is significant
so
h a b which is
the physical interaction between a and b
and hence the boundary the holographic
screen between a and b
must have significantly lower dimension
than
the physical location of b and hence the
observable dynamics of b
if the weak interaction limit is to hold
um my brain is melting now
all the way down
so
yeah anyway what do you think do you
have any thoughts on that
um not sure if it means that the sparse
coupling has to be sufficiently sparse
it has to be a lot lower dimension than
the system
otherwise it's um
not appropriately
bottlenecked
so there's a lower dimensional interface
that's like sparse coupling it's
physical interaction in the h
frame and it's the holograph slash
markov blanket with the fancy b
but if the interaction is with the h and
that's kind of what we'll
discuss like are we talking about
physical interactions of quantum systems
or we're talking about any mechanistic
interaction between any mechanistic
system or are we talking about
statistical edges statistical
interactions like an interaction term
between two different systems
um and so just what i've written down
here kind of
paraphrases what they said uh up there
so the ability for a system a to predict
the dynamics of system b depends on the
dynamic complexity of the interaction
between system b
um which is pb on the holographic screen
so what is b writing to the holographic
screen like what is my refrigerator
writing to the holographic screen um i
would say that's a trivial system right
it's like outputting a little bit of
heat it keeps my food a little bit cold
most of the time so i can with pretty
good reliability predict the dynamics of
my refrigerator i have less ability to
predict the dynamics of daniel or my
children who are like total agents of
chaos right
so but but
like i want to minimize my uncertainty
i'm pretty certain about what my
refrigerator is doing i don't know what
my kids are doing when i leave the room
um yeah
so that that kind of made sense to me
but
the schrodinger's cat to blue's children
pipeline
we just got there
um anything else to out here dana
no let's
moving forward okay so here is
a little diagram of what it looks like
for me to predict the dynamics of my
refrigerator
so so this is figure 6 a
um it says the trivial agent
in figure 6 a look like a noise source
to a so yes my refrigerator is a source
of noise it just like it actually
literally makes noise um and you know
puts out a little bit of heat
so it says emission of hawking radiation
from a black hole provides perhaps the
most pure example of such a noise source
while the dimension inside the black
hole can be arbitrarily large the
internal dynamics are uncoupled from the
classical information encoded on the
horizon and hence have no classical
computational power
yes
okay maybe refrigerator has more
computational power than a black hole i
don't know
okay
we move on here we go forward
so the more interesting parts of a's
option space for prediction are shown in
panel b c and d
where b is non-trivial
if b is non-trivial it deploys at least
one quantum reference frame
x of b like so that's sector x of b
acting on sector x b
uh
as discussed in section 2.5 b sectors
must be mutually decoherent
so the action of the dynamics
on the sector of b is independent of
action elsewhere is this independence
that makes prediction possible
if x of b does not overlap any sector
um
for a b will appear trivial so like if
the green cone is totally removed from
what the red cone is like
it's a trivial thing like if you know my
kids aren't here right now they're not
immediately acting on my environment um
so
they're trivial i guess or
this made me think about like if if
someone was speaking a language that you
didn't understand semantically
not even in the queues and in the
metadata like there's kind of speaking
past each other even though you're
sharing a screen
but that's like an intentional
informational interpretation
and this is in a quantum interpretation
about the shared semantic frame ranging
from identical
to overlapping to disjoint
so in in a disjoint um
way i'm trying to think of what else
would be there so like a different
language is good but like
what about something like radiation
emission right like so something's
emitting radiation but i can't perceive
that radiation so like the thing
emitting radiation doesn't appear like
it's impacting my environment at all so
maybe something like that
and i'd like maybe unobserved
the part of of be the holograph that's
not
in the observed or memory sector
yeah like that
um okay cool
so
the interesting cases are the ones in
which a and b's observable sectors
overlap
in this case intuitively in which a and
b can see each other and hence interact
in the ordinary non-technical sense of
that term
in panel b sector xb fully contains
xa
um
yeah
okay so let's go here let's look at the
at the whole figure now so we saw all
the ones trivial and non-trivial okay so
a is a trivial agent so they're not
putting out any
um b encodes a sector that contains xa
but is bigger
so i like to think about this as like um
a teacher so we're going to get into
like teaching and learning so this is
like a teacher that knows more than the
student can pick up
maybe um
in that kind of way so the bits on xb
but outside xa encode non-local hidden
variables for a
and then in diagram c the sectors of x a
and x b overlap the areas of non-overlap
become noise sources so here it's like
um you know
i can understand you when you speak
english but not when you speak chinese
so like when you're speaking chinese we
have this non-overlapping
frame
anyway how do you think of that dan
um this is just speculative but um
in the case of b so we're the observer
investigator a
so in the case of of frame b there's so
much information like in the linear
regression data set by quantum that
there's basically anywhere we look we
can totally get all the information so
it looks like there's non-local hidden
variables because it's like super
determined in the case of c
the regression has like an r squared of
0.5 or something or 0.6
and so some of it lines up semantically
but if we of course had the perfect
attention or the perfect observation
we would be able to make a better
regression
but then like i'm just trying to take
the linear regression
normal information framework and then
that's where having people familiar with
quantum
will be really helpful and i hope they
find this discussion and
upcoming
1.1.2 as like just the introduction of
hopefully some bi-directional exchange
because this may be
something where active inference is
complementary isomorphic incompatible
like let's not lose
touch with the active inference thread
and then
also how is this relating to quantum and
that's how we're going to get up in that
quadrant where they both are
yeah so in d
where the um
sector of x is equal to the sector of or
sorry the sector x of a is equal to the
sector x of b
um so that means that the quantum
reference frame is identical it's an
identical frame like we're we are
sharing a quantum reference we're both
standing on the platform or we're both
on the train um and so that sector a is
equal to sector b any variational free
energy there between a and b is
generated by insufficient learning it's
not like we both can't see the train
or we both can't see the platform
because we're in the same place but um
so there's somebody there is doing some
insufficient learning
if this is the case then you just simply
need to sample more
but you already have the right scope and
you're not at risk of over sampling
but it's a little bit more quantum
cool
and that brings us to this beautiful
formulation in
equation 41.
variational free energy equals noise
plus insufficient learning
so noise is capturing that bottom left
part
that we just discussed and insufficient
is capturing the d case
and so
if it was uh
more and more overlapping
then you want more and more sampling
but less and less overlapping is going
to require less and less learning or
learning will be less and less helpful
so how is this
compatible incompatible with the actin
framings that we've seen for vfe
and efe
and then how is this compatible or
similar to
some of the formalisms and the framings
that are really familiar to
statisticians into quantum information
scientists
[Music]
and i would also like to like
know what teachers think so if you're a
teacher and you're watching this
like like what what is your take on that
do you minimize free energy
by minimizing
noise and
you know maximizing learning or or yeah
like that okay
um
cool so asymptotic behavior of the fvp
so we have these two formulations
surprise loan divergence which we've
seen before
in a similar way many times and then
noise plus insufficient learning so now
we want to say how is it minimized how
does an agent act in accordance with the
fep
what do you want to add here yeah just
they wrote comparing equations 35 and 41
it becomes clear what this amounts to
a system self evidence is by behaving in
a way that minimizes noise while
improving learning
and so here they're juxtaposing the
f of pi
on surprisal and divergence
decomposition of variational free energy
with this noise plus insufficient
learning
framing
so we'll have time to unpack that and
hopefully connect it to some systems but
it's just a very
interesting
way that they've reached this trade-off
learning requires
seeking it's like
how do we get there
well that goes back to the um to the
context switching like if you're always
in the same context like if you're
always you know listening to the same
music you're never gonna learn
any new music that someone else might
know like or or so you have to kind of
change
um change your context maybe take
someone else's perspective but you know
seeking what
but we'll get there
yes okay so
let's also save this let's save this for
one but the asymptotic behavior of the
fep let's just say why does it matter
why are we studying asymptotic systems
what is happening with the fpp
asymptotically
asymptotically meaning what
but i think that that's a large
discussion
about entanglement and where everything
is going
and how it relates to the principle of
unitarity
yes
okay
cool
just
we'll get there in dot one
unitary
there's only one more sliders is the how
yeah the fep drives
um it is it becomes the principle of
unitarity so
we can we can discuss that in dot ones
better how does it does it why does it
matter why would it matter
cool um
okay
discussion
travis home please okay
we're just gonna we're not gonna discuss
any of the discussion
here
we're going to look at the summary of
the results as they give it
and then we're going to have a bunch of
slides that will just be like a topic
and then with the dot one and the dot
two we're just gonna go to that topic
and probably start with just reading a
quote from that paragraph
or hearing the authors or the
participant's perspective on like
each of those topics
cool
okay
do you want to you can go for the
summary
come on help me out okay
you you read the three just the three um
big texts at the very beginning
but the first
summary of the results that the um
authors say
is that they can formulate this agent
or information gathering and using
system
not just within the
classical information theory context
that we've been talking about
informational and strategic agents but
in the context of quantum information
theory
point two
is not just
using a generic agent or information
gathering using system
but specifically connecting the fep
to its quantum theoretic formulation
for generic quantum systems
insert all the asterisks and other
symbols about what that really means
and about how active inference plays in
etc
and then
three the part that we didn't really go
into in this discussion when formulated
as a generic principle of quantum
information theory the fep is
asymptotically equivalent to the
principle of unitarity
and under asked in the chat
asymptotically in what parameter just
exactly to what ends in what parameter
so that's the summary of the results but
the authors then
embark on
an awesome
series of
kind of like standalone
paragraph vignettes
related to a wide
set of other ideas
so for each of these ideas
i'll um ask the question on the top and
then if you want to give a thought
on that topic or not okay so the first
topic is
yeah
let me answer the question so it says
actually asymptotically perfect learning
so that's the asymptotically perfect
finding that drives to unitary on one
axis so anyway okay um
what is observation
that's deep
several paragraphs they wrote about that
and this quote um
the idea
of a metaphysically
solipsistic
or solipsist
theory of observation is
self-contradictory
what
but we'll
discuss
okay
what is an agent
and again we'll keep in mind classical
physics
classical fep non-classical fep
that where are we
bigger
from earlier
i'll copy
that one back in
because this is definitely like a where
are we like what are the similarities
and differences
in the agent model
for
fep and not and for quantum and not
any thoughts or like things that you'll
want to ask about this
what is free choice i think that's that
was cool um
yeah
and like
do you get
degrees of freedom or free choice over
cognitive parameters action parameters
which one do you want
choice over or all of them
preferences okay
what is self-evidencing
so we've talked in several other
discussions
about
classical or bayesian inference as
self-evidencing
like finding oneself in likely states
expected in preferred states
how is that
different in active than other physics
that's like going from the bottom left
to the bottom right
and then how is this different within
active inference
with this quantum
integration and boost
yes
okay
what of
asymptotic behavior
yeah um so i think here it's the
asymptotically perfect learning
like what is a gauge theoretic
perspective i don't even want to open
that kind of worms at all
so yeah also this is like the quantum
formulation the quantum formalism is
background free
space is simply an observable
represented by a qrf
that a system may or may not deploy
it can therefore play no on-tech role in
maintaining distinctions between systems
this reflects the general role of
physical 3d space in quantum field
theories
space is there to enforce separability
c68 for general discussion from a gauge
theoretical perspective
so like the space between
is what
i'm gonna also um copy in a comment that
underwrote in the live chat
just
anyone who asks questions um
you know just put it in live chat or put
as a comment under the video
or email us but
it helps us and it's awesome questions
that people ask okay
we will definitely look at this before
we do that one and so if you you're
welcome to join us get in touch if you
want to participate live but also like
we will ask these questions if we leave
them in the chat
yeah okay let's go to
close out almost kind of getting there
applications to biological cognition
um
and then they wrote in this paper
in addition to the results listed above
the current framework
so the paper we've been discussing
has a variety of more specifically
biological consequences some of which
have been discussed already in citation
13.
and here's citation 13 fields glaze
broke 11
minimal physicalism as a scale-free
substrate for cognition and
consciousness and here's the sections of
that
paper
and so it's just kind of cool to connect
back to the basal cognition
computational boundaries of a self
discussion that we've been having live
stream number 39 just
today
um and we also have uh
neurons as hierarchies of quantum
reference frames which i haven't read
yet um that this was just published in
january of 22. i think that was
co-released with this paper so
i'm i'm excited to
read that work also
awesome so yeah what are the biological
implications okay
um
quantum frames
for foraging
so
unique explanations and predictions it
predicts for example that moving in
ordinary 3d space does not require a qrf
for euclidean space
and hence does not require an experience
of space
so like the fish could swim without
knowing 3d
and then from a classical perspective
okay so i guess that means non-fep and
or non-quantum
this is certainly true evidence by place
and grid cells in mammalian brains etc
and then what happens when we integrate
fep in the classical
well the course graining would then be
mandated by et cetera et cetera we'll
explore okay then what happens if we go
from classical to classical fep and then
now go from fep to quantum fep
still thinking about like foraging
or information seeking and processing
okay
contextuality
we talked about that a lot in 171
but just
what is context environment
surrounding
is this what people mean when they say
set the context for the dinner party
or give context for a video that they
sent
what is that everyday sense of context
and what is this sense of context
okay
next steps so these are the last two
lines of the paper
and they wrote
in closing we hope that we have shown to
readers familiar with the fep and active
inference framework that quantum effects
are worth considering both theoretically
and in experimental design
for readers not familiar with the
classical fa ep but literate in quantum
theory
or vice versa
we hope this paper has gone some way to
contextualizing your qrfs incense making
via markov blankets and their underlying
holographic screens
so this is like saying
if you were familiar with either quantum
not fep upper left
or classical fep
bottom right or maybe bottom left
neither
then this paper
hopefully brought you towards that upper
right corner of quantum fep
and just like
the
classical classical way to end an fep
paper was like we expect and prefer that
this reduces your uncertainty
this is like the classical quantum way
to end the paper by saying
we hope it's contextualized your qrf
the clever ending
to
a very complex paper
and
it was really fun to work on this for a
couple weeks
leading up to these discussions and
what else would you say as we now head
into the dot one and two
yeah so like thanks for putting up with
our rough interpretation of this paper
and we hope we didn't butcher it too
badly yeah um
we tried yeah if if you know more or
would like to contribute to helping
others know more about these topics
that's what we're working on all the
time in actin flap so if you've made it
this far
and you're riled up or curious about
something then
get in touch and let's try to make
all of this more
handleable
and able to be translated and learned
and applied
yeah let's try to align our quantum
reference frames
with respect to actin
what else can we say
all right so see you all
um soon thanks a lot blue thanks also
jason and thanks everybody who will
participate in the upcoming ones too
so see you later bye
you